[Music]
so we record an interview that went
partly into the glitch in the matrix
film and it was shared like a few people
took clips for it and it was widely
shared I think one of them got about
250,000 views in total probably about
half a million people saw that interview
and what we talked about a lot was the
female shadow and the idea that what we
we're living in a culture that
especially with me too has got a sort of
real exposure of the male shadow and
these sort of ways that men have acted
out and but and this kind of ongoing
narrative of toxic masculinity but we
have no no one talks about toxic
femininity and how to really unbalance
conversation did what were those sort of
responses that you got to that so I got
a lot of responses from men around the
world really thanking me for speaking up
from for saying something that they
don't feel that they could speak and
they haven't heard other women say so
they really thank me for bringing a
voice to something that's there but it's
not spoken about there's no permission
to speak about these things and I had
also women messaging me to say thank you
for showing up in this way thank you for
showing womanhood so there's something
about a way in a conversation that we
haven't brought into the picture that
that somehow resonated with many people
and also I know that there were some
people who thought that you were
speaking from a position of internalized
misogyny of course let's you know that's
the first thing that people are going to
question where's this woman come coming
from because she's saying something that
you're not allowed to say and of course
I had a lot of self-reflection about is
that true or not and of course that's a
I grew up in a patriarchal society I
grew up with these with these values I
grew up feeling as a girl and as a woman
that my voice was not was not as
important and
and it's worth listening to so I had to
think about has I've been internalized
in me and I would say yes and no but I
know very well how it is to be a woman
and I know how it is to be a woman in a
public space so the place that I'm
coming from is really from from an
experience of being a woman
and also being in a deep relationship
with a man that teaches me about how is
it to be a man and as a mother of two
young men as well that are developing
their masculinity in contemporary
society that teaches me a lot and that's
a place that I'm speaking from it's
really from this embodied experience of
being a woman right now this is what I
wanted to to say about the me to
movement that yes it has exposed male
shadows but it has definitely also
exposed female shadows this blind
aggression the blind projections that
are going on towards men and this is
what this is what we're not allowed to
talk about and this is what is important
for women to really look at and to
really have a sane self-reflection about
how are we actually trying to create the
space that we're missing are we trying
to create it from the place of the
shadow that we are taking we are
becoming the perpetrators ourselves our
aggressive and on reflected voices and
these are attacking people by playing
the victim attacking men basically
attacking men for being the perpetrators
but in a way with that we do it
ourselves instead of taking the space
and filling it with what is it actually
to be a woman this is really this is
missing what is being exposed now that
being a woman is that we have so much
power and we are going to use it quite
irresponsibly this is what I see with a
me-too movement that it's gone too far
it's like we are we're becoming
increasing okay women sisters what do we
want to
with this space that we have created
because I guess what we're saying is yes
me too exposed male shadows but we all
have shadows women have shadows just as
men have shadows and they're probably
different and also there's some sense
like Harvey Weinstein is now facing he's
been charged with rape he's facing a
long time in jail potentially so for a
long time there's this kind of narrative
of well the patriarchy Harvey Weinstein
was facilitated by the patriarchy it's
like well that same patriarchy the legal
system the structures that we've built
in society has now held him accountable
and it looks like he's probably going to
go to jail and actually I would argue if
if people both men and women within
within his circles had spoken up earlier
and taken moral responsibility rather
than accepting payoffs and rather than
kind of and actually stood up and said
something we wouldn't be in this
situation now so you could say oh yeah
well it's a corrupt system I'd agree but
it was only corrupt because the people
in it were corrupt the actual system
itself when people spoke up is
functioning as it should the justice
system is functioning as it should and
this I think could perhaps for me at
least were kind of before or after
moment because for a long time there's
been this sort of sense of and the
you've active heard people say this it's
like men now it's not your time to speak
you just have to listen and I can
understand that and I have been
listening to a lot of the stories that
have come out and a lot of them are
horrific and it's like a real point of
kind of reflection but it can't stay
there because if it's just one person
speaking another person listening by
definition that's not a relationship a
relationship by definition is you speak
I listen I speak you listen if if it's
not then it's it's not a relationship
it's a master/slave dynamic or it's a
power dispute or it's a dominance
hierarchy game it's not a relationship
so the relationship that needs to happen
it seems is yes for men to listen to
women's experience but women also have
to listen to men
experience as well and then we could see
sort of some progress in this kind of
discussion beyond just the the kind of
the victim perpetrator dynamic that we
seem to be being pulled into yeah this
is the thing that I I feel is the most
important about the meter movement is
that it was somehow doomed to happen
this lid needed to explode or this
container needed to explode because
women couldn't contain it anymore so
it's coming out so let's say that's the
initiation of a conversation but then it
started running a bit amok because it's
not a conversation it's it's it's a
getting out the rage which is very
understandable and very needed but then
is a question what are we going to do
with this how we going to be responsible
about the things that we have
experienced and the place that we want
to take in society the power that we
want to have the disempowerment we don't
want to feel anymore
how are we going to bring that to the
world and the way that it's been
happening is not that it's a chaotic way
it's a blame way it's a female shadow
coming up and I'm I'm really really
interested in women showing up with men
in connection to say what's going on
wrong for you what's going on wrong for
me it's a self-reflection that really
really needs to happen that I haven't
seen yet I've seen like the explosion
that creates a space but there's a next
phase is to fill it with the content and
men and women need to do that in
dialogue and in respect for the
differences which is also what's lacking
there's men there's women
there's masculine that's feminine
there's male as female all these things
what does that mean it's not the same
there is a difference and what do we do
in that space this is what I'm really
interested in what do we do in this
space I mean we are if you're watching
this and you live in London or you live
in the UK we're doing an event on the
5th of June to try and model these
conversations and try and bring it to
that next level coz I think I think it
has to happen in person
I think these only things can only have
in person I want to add to that that it
is a thing that always needs to happen
in person because we can sit there and
we can have intellectual discussions
about men and women our position in
society and everything but when we walk
down of the room and we go out there we
go back to our partners and our life
that's where it's really happening it's
really happening at the interpersonal
experience a level and that's where we
can learn so much about how am I in
connection how am I in relationship how
am i playing out these shadows here now
and we really forget about it and that's
why that's a micro level where the real
learning is so that we can change
society at the macro level yeah I mean
what it feels like is happening I mean
what he was happening is men and women
in this sort of dysfunctional
relationship is I think one of the key
the key drivers of what we're seeing in
the political realm what we're seeing in
a cultural realm at the moment which has
risen with sort of women's position in
the world at post-1960
as many women are sharing space more and
more which is an essential development
but also there are these difficulties
about navigating kind of men's and
women's different experience of the
world one thing I also want to say is
and this apparently was not acceptable
but you weren't allowed to say this but
myself and most of the guys that I know
our issue we weren't raised by the same
people who are raising Harvey Weinstein
and that sort of older generation of men
mark our issues I can speak for myself
and speak for a lot of the guys that I
know were not kind of internalizing rape
culture and abuse it was far more about
castration like we were castration in
our in our families and castration in a
wider culture and what I mean by that is
it's not okay you're competitive drives
are not okay your aggression is not okay
all of these sort of aspects of yourself
that we as men have more of with the
sort of testosterone and our biological
existence and I'm not okay and then it
sort of no this is toxic masculinity and
I teach men's
groups and the number of men who've
internalized a sense of shame around
themselves as men is huge and this is
the dynamic now and at the moment we're
having this sort of reaction against an
old dynamic with Harvey Weinstein and
people who are raised by sort of 1950s
1960s parents who that probably was more
kind of internalized misogyny in those
areas I think what we're seeing now is a
much more complex picture and it's
generally sort of a castration that
either comes from the family or comes
from kind of our dynamics or comes from
the culture where it's this this
masculinity is being shamed and this is
a completely different dynamic and it's
one that's I think added to by the me2
or some of the me2 movement which when
meet who says men are you the only
appropriate response now is to shut up
and listen and to feel guilty for
yourself and food and it's like there's
some truth in yeah we as men need to
hold our brothers accountable and hold
ourselves accountable in the same way
that we all need to hold each other
accountable but to kind of internalized
that there's something faulty about you
as a man is it's really is a really
dangerous thing to give to someone so
when you mention castration I absolutely
agree that this is happening at so many
levels in in society right now and in
the values in the institutions and I
feel it's somehow it's a movement it's
it's the evolution from the modernist to
the post modernist set of values of
mindset paradigm that we moved from a
patriarchal structure into no that
doesn't work anymore we need to we
really need to question everything and
we've done that we've ended up in the
postmodern questioning all values but
the thing is that with that with the
destruction of the patriarchy has come
the feminization of society it's like
the post-modern
it's not just no values because it is
essentially feminine but this is this is
fascinating because the the dialogue
that goes with that is that that's not
true there's a kind of as a kind of
almost gas lighting going on where we're
being told that no we're still living in
a patriarchal society everything is
still patriarchal when is actually it's
pretty feminized you look at kind of
masculine values and the way boys are
treated in school and the fact that
they're kind of natural exuberance is
now being seen as toxic we are living in
a feminized society that's pretending
that it's not and claiming that actually
no no it's still patriarchal and this is
it's kind of this very trip difficult
sort of perspective to hold at the same
time I think it's a natural place that
we need need to move through it was
patriarchal masculinity is moved into we
need to we need to rebel against that so
it's post-modernism that that says
everything is has is inherently the same
there is no difference and we need to
treat boys and girls like the same and
you know I see this happening and even
the micro level of of schools and you
know institutions but the thing is it's
a feminine way of thinking that we are
all the same it's community it's really
caring caring for the whole and it's not
expensive it's an important it's a very
important perspective we need to include
it and transcend this transcend and
include is so essential if we want to
move forward in cult if we really want
to think in an evolutionary way and say
yes we've feminized our Institute our
institutions we've feminized our values
but we are throwing out the baby with
the bathwater and this is where a person
like Jordan Peterson comes on this on
the scene and says there's something
wrong here something is missing he
becomes a very very important voice
that's a result of that feminization is
the way I see it so yeah there's a few
pieces of really interesting pieces
cut there and the most interesting one
is that what is the synthesis so if if
you have sort of this patriarchal system
which I would say so you've got this
sort of conspiracy theory of the
patriarchy which i think is just this it
is a conspiracy theory it's an
oversimplification because if you see
men as just dominating women throughout
history then you just that's just wrong
because it obscures the self-sacrifice
that men have had the fact that a lot of
them probably haven't wanted to do the
jobs that they've done and that they
have basically sacrificed a lot of their
inner life to be able to have to do that
to support people and the disposability
of men throughout history and all of
this stuff like it it's one side of a
dynamic that so that conspiracy theory
is is is not true why there is some
truth and the idea of the patriarchy is
because we are in the West we've all had
to kind of suppress a lot of the more
intuitive direct forms of knowing we've
had this or a very rationalist culture
that's done incredible things like this
kind of it's created these incredible
structures and also the idea that
feminine values don't scale masculine
value if you want to kind of create a
society that treats people equally then
the the masculine value of the justice
system and stuff that's it works for for
scale feminine values of inclusivity and
making sure that everyone is included
and that no one is excluded and you
don't offend anyone may work for small
groups I think any works particularly
well for small groups if it's taken to
the extreme but it doesn't work on a
wider scale it actually starts leading
to censorship and I fear I think we're
already kind of in a slow-motion
dictatorship of the mind like there are
stuff that we are not allowed to say
anymore and this is what's really
terrifying about what I what I feel that
we're we're going into and I think a lot
of it is this sort of this feminine this
sort of darker feminine energy that's
kind of infiltrating the culture I want
to say I think that this the tyranny of
the mind we've kind of always been in
that you know that's the whole problem
that
in in Western culture and that's been
somehow the dominating world culture
it's it's it's society of the mind we
are thinking about the world in abstract
terms and that's you know that's how
patriarchy is based it's based on
abstract thinking it's not based on
connecting to life on the feminine
values and when you're talking about
synthesis what I think is really really
interesting is to see okay what can we
create when the clear masculine values
and the clear feminine values are
allowed to be at the same time what
you're saying maps on to one of the best
descriptions I've seen is by Richard
tarnis he wrote this book or the passion
of the Western mind about and because
and this is also at the root of I think
a lot of the crises that we're seeing at
the moment is because we cut ourselves
off from a deep part of ourselves but
this mashup this male rationalist
materialist worldview has cut off the
intuitive the archetype or the religious
the the thing that gives us meaning and
I think this is why this is the crisis
that we're seeing and the way through it
is actually a kind of return of the
intelligent integrated feminine and this
is and this is why I think that Peterson
he's channeling like this this old
spirit of the divine masculine and it is
absolutely essential we cannot do
without it and he is channeling this
thing into the culture in a big way and
his successes shows how much we're
thirsting for it this this important
masculine energy but it needs to be
matched by a feminine energy of equal
power and weight because and I think
this is this is why I think there is
some truth in like the New York Times
article called and custodian of the
patriarchy I think on some level I do
think he may and may be quite rightly is
concerned about what's happened since
the 60s
like we have started sharing space
between men and women is that going to
work out or is there not going to work
out we don't know it's clearly creating
huge difficulties and I think he's
genuinely not sure whether it's a good
idea
idea I think people are picking up on
that and criticizing him for it but
ultimately we're not going to wind the
clock back we are going to have to go
through and forward and find this
synthesis which is going to be as Jordan
Greenhalgh talks about what we have and
he also frames it by saying these are
very difficult conversations to have
these are hugely important but very
difficult conversations to have we have
the feminine rising into power power and
we also need the feminine to rise into
responsibility at the same time and
those two things need to happen need to
happen at the same time and it's it's
certainly true that women now have power
to destroy men destroy men's reputations
destroy men's careers and that power and
it's it's right that some people do have
their careers destroyed and some people
do have the reputations ruined that's
right we're not going back to the 1950s
sort of madmen culture but also that
with great power comes great
responsibility
I think for me what woke me up as a
woman about Jordan Peterson was that he
was beginning to talk about a longing in
culture along him we are in this time of
cares and where are the axioms where are
the things that are true at a deeper
levels and you know as women we already
know that there are these truths we've
just been really really trained to not
feel it and not speak it and he speaks
to that but and I really like the way
that he's saying hello man where are you
where is a divine masculine because the
divine feminine has has come massively
into the world none of the divine
feminine but you know that with a lot of
shadow as well Carly exactly chopping
off and saying enough yeah but it's run
amok and we need the divine masculine we
need to strong the deep the mature
masculine to stand up and say I'm here
and we need we need the feminine to do
the same and that's what I feel is is
what Peterson is is pointing yet but
miss
and he's speaking more he's speaking
more to men he's speaking notes of the
masculine I don't feel that he's saying
the feminine is not important at all but
he's creating a space and I want women
to stand up and say okay what is this
space from a woman's perspective how can
we fill this space but this and this
also you were just saying the Divine
Feminine is showing up a lot of Carly at
the moment brilliant kind of archetypal
framework and it's like and it's
absolutely right that she does because
men need to find their their grounding
men need to find their balls men need to
find to stand in their masculinity and
say enough women test men to see how
grounded they are that happens
automatically it needs to happen
women evolutionarily that has to happen
women have to test men like you women
had a far bigger investment in
childbirth and bringing up children and
so women constantly test men and they
it's an evolutionary necessity and it's
actually something that's very valuable
to men too for that to happen it's like
that's how we evolve is is through that
kind of being tested and standing in our
truths and standing in our masculinity
and women are very there's a kind of
idea of men or concert men test ideas
and women test men it's very easy to
misunderstand that and say well do you
mean women don't have ideas that's
outrageous dude it is no but that has
always been the truth women have a much
more direct kind of sense of when
someone's really aligned when someone's
really grounded so men may test ideas
but they may not be connected to any
sort of deeper emotional truth and they
can go off on all sorts of directions
women in the past have been really good
at kind of seeing where the alignment is
and I think men are developing more
emotional intelligence are more able to
do that than before but I still think
women have a deeper lived biological
reality of really really seeing that
deeper alignment and that's why the me
to discussion again that's why it's
really interesting because it shows
these dynamics because what's been
happening
right now is that women have really
really gone from him and really really
testing and said speaking up challenging
and what's happened is that men have
kind of retreated to the corner gotten
defensive or have really lost their
masculinity giving away their balls and
what we're not seeing is that men are
stepping up and saying okay enough but
from a grounded perspective from a
perspective of hearing and embracing the
pain but also saying that there's a
limit here because the feminine needs
that that it's it's no fun if we keep
running and running and and and nailing
men per se on everything like creating a
society where where where men are
dangerous for women and this is what you
know that's that's a danger for what's
happening if we don't have a much more
balanced conversation about this because
as women we don't want all the power we
want we want to share that space and and
it seems like we both forgotten that we
so we're so engaged in the antagonism in
clearing the space that we forget why
we're clearing it what one I'm gonna
come back to what do we want to fill
that space with what is the synthesis
look like what does the what would a
healthy relationship look like I love
this question because this is the most
open question we can have right now I
don't have the answer this is what we're
developing together right now this is
why I want to say to my my sister's all
the women are there come on let's do
that let's find out what is it to be a
woman because we've forgotten with Luke
we've totally cut off from from those
roots and let the men figure out what is
it about to be a man and let's come
together and see what happens in that
space if we are all the same in
post-modernism nothing is happening this
is why we see our society isn't isn't a
complete crisis this is only gonna get
worse because we don't have we don't
have a salut
and this is why we need a co-creation a
synthesis to go to the next level we
can't go to the next level on our own
the resources the the physical resources
of the planet the mental resources out
of our thinking they are exhausted they
are not creating that next level that we
need to go to and this is why for me
this whole discussion between men and
women between the feminine and the
masculine these archetypes they are so
essential because they are leading us to
the next point of evolution so I don't
have the answer what is that but I want
to say let's find out yeah and let's
start finding out on next Tuesday do you
see this 5th of June so we are hosting a
evolutionary conversation around these
topics details I think will be below
like down there down there below the the
video in youtube and yeah I want to
start this conversation I want to I want
us to be hosting regular events where we
can start just bringing this up to
another level I think we've got to a
point with the the me to campaign now
especially with a sort of watershed
moment of kind of Harvey Weinstein being
prosecuted and I think we're now we're
now at a place where we can start to
kind of move on from from this sort of
one side of conversation and start
having a full conversation it's very
very exciting time
you